Preface

The writer of this book, Malcolm Logan Stevenson, was born in the year 1891. On the death of his father, in 1895, the boy came under the care of his uncle, Sir Lionel Cope, the greater part of his boyhood being spent at Courton Hall in West Sussex. He was educated at Winchester and New College. Throughout his life his financial position was such as to cause him no anxiety; he was, in fact, a man of very considerable estate.

As a young man he displayed little enthusiasm for any form of regular occupation, in marked distinction to his later life. His interests at that time were essentially in things adventurous rather than academic. From Oxford he joined the ill–fated Catter–Delina expedition to the Amazon, leaving this country for Para in the autumn of 1911. He returned to England with the survivors of that party in the spring of 1913 and devoted himself with some energy to the sport of yacht cruising, an exercise to which he was much attached. In the winter of 1913 he commenced a desultory study of the economic factors affecting commercial ships and shipping, spending some months upon the Clyde. Previous to the war, however, he made no venture in this business.

In September, 1914, he was granted a commission as Sub–Lieutenant in the RNVR, and served upon minesweepers until the summer of 1917, principally in the Channel and the Irish Sea. During this period his vessel was twice mined; in the second of these explosions he lost the third and fourth fingers of his left hand.

In September, 1917, he was promoted to Lieutenant and was posted to a so–called mystery ship, the Jane Ellen, of Bideford, under Commander D. A. Faulkner, RN. This vessel was a coastal schooner of some one hundred and fifty tons, normally trading in china clay and coal between the southern ports of Cornwall and the north–east coast. Under Commander Faulkner she was employed as a submarine decoy.

The action of the Jane Ellen (HMS Q 83) will be found described in a supplement to the London Gazette published shortly after the Armistice, together with the list of awards. Sir Arthur Mortimer, in the second volume of his ‘Naval History of the Great War’, gives a reliable account of the engagement, which he refers to as ‘one of the bloodiest naval actions ever fought’. Briefly, the Jane Ellen engaged the U187 at dawn, on April 18th, 1918, at a point some forty miles west of the Scillies. Casualties on the British vessel were extremely heavy and included the Commander, the ship’s company of forty–seven being reduced eventually to three in number. Finally the U187 was sunk by gunfire at about noon, the gun being manned by Lieutenant Stevenson and a midshipman. No survivors were rescued from the German vessel.

As a result of this action Stevenson was promoted to Lieutenant–Commander; he was then about twenty–seven years of age. Injuries to his lungs, aggravated by exposure, necessitated a prolonged period in hospital subsequent to the action. It would not be beyond the truth to say that these injuries were ultimately responsible for his early death.

In the spring of 1919 Commander Stevenson commenced to build up a fleet of schooners and small ketches which had carried the bulk of the coastwise traffic of this country before the war. At that time these vessels had disappeared almost entirely from British waters. A certain number of them were sold abroad during the war; the remainder were sunk as they carried on their business.

In the years following the war Commander Stevenson repurchased a number of these vessels from their Scandinavian owners and, establishing himself in a shipyard on the River Dart, commenced to operate them in their ancient trade. At the time of his death he was the owner of no less than seventeen of these ships. At the outset this speculation involved him in a financial loss which was severe even for a man of his resources; in later years the losses decreased, and at the time of his death the business was in a fair way to show a profit.

In the settlement of his estate the fleet was broken up, the majority of the vessels being sold abroad again. It is doubtful whether this form of coastwise trading can be regarded as an economic business in these days. It is at least doubtful whether Commander Stevenson cared if it were so or not.

From the year 1919 until his death, ten years later, he lived in the Port House above Dartmouth Harbour, alone but for a housekeeper and a few servants. As the business of his fleet became stereotyped, demanding less of his attention, he showed some inclination to develop his shipyard as a building centre for yachts and small sailing craft of various kinds.

In the winter of last year he died, after a comparatively short illness, at the early age of thirty–nine.

* * * * *

In person, Malcolm Stevenson was a man of medium height; his hair, from the war onwards, was almost completely grey. He walked with a slight limp; he was sensitive to the injury to his left hand, for which reason he usually wore a glove. In temperament he was very taciturn, perhaps bitter. He was popular with his acquaintances but admitted few to friendship; with women he was diffident and shy. He had few interests beyond the sea. For recreation he was accustomed to cruise single–handed, or with at most one friend, in his tenton cutter Runagate; he was a regular competitor in the Ocean Race. He was a member of the Squadron. He held both Master’s and Extra Master’s certificates, and on occasions when he was short of a skipper would sometimes act as Master in one of his own little ships upon a coastal cruise.

He had few relatives, and those few he neglected. His closest tie was with his cousin, Lady Stenning. In the later years of his life he seldom left Dartmouth except to stay at her house in Golders Green, and he became on terms of considerable friendship, if not intimacy, with her husband, Sir Philip Stenning. To Sir Philip he left a very considerable legacy; for the remainder, his testament was eccentric and beyond the scope of this preface.

* * * * *

The book which is now published was written by Commander Stevenson shortly before the illness which terminated in his death. The MS is written in pencil in a foolscap ledger freely interspersed with memoranda of a personal nature; it would seem from internal evidence that the compilation of this book was a relaxation for his leisure hours over a period of about two months.

In the settlement of his estate the MS was read first by the writer of this preface, and later by Sir Philip and Lady Stenning, who confirmed the truth of the account. It seemed desirable, and even necessary, that the facts contained therein should be made public at an early date, for which reason it was first proposed that a condensed and impersonal edition of the narrative should be prepared. Upon a closer investigation, however, it became evident that the task of expurgation would prove to be a most formidable one, and that a great mass of extraneous matter would require to be inserted in explanation of motives which were wholly personal and therefore to be omitted from the book. In these circumstances it has seemed better to publish the MS substantially in the form in which it was discovered, only modifying those names and places which bear too close a relation to the world as it is lived in today.

With this course the relatives of Commander Stevenson are in agreement. I am indebted to Sir Lionel Cope for advice upon matters pertaining to the family, and to Lady Stenning for much assistance in the preparation of the narrative. If the effect of publication in this form should be to indicate a quality of greatness in a man of singular reserve, then the intrusion into his privacy may not be quite unjustified.

T. A. Jenkinson Messrs. Louden, Jenkinson, and Priestly, Lincoln’s Inn Fields, London.

Chapter 9

We went on board at once. Outside the harbour a light breeze had sprung up from the north–east; I set to work and got the anchor short, and got the main on her alone. Then with the engine ticking over and with Mollie at the helm I broke her out and set the jib and foresail, and stood out into the Bay.

I kept her off the wind and sailing free until I had the anchor catted and all square forward; then I came aft and luffed her for the open sea. Mollie was by me in the cockpit as we crossed the Bay; I taught her how to steer the vessel on a wind and how to mark the trembling of the luff. But all the glamour of that day was gone. It was still bright and sunny, a calm sea and a steady sailing breeze: the fault was in ourselves.

Once she turned to me and said: “Please, Commander Stevenson. Shall I have to go and tell the police about Edna and Billy now?”

I did not answer for a moment, but stood staring at the land down Brixham way, still wreathed about with summer haze. And then I looked at her, and smiled. “I hadn’t thought about it much,” I said. “One thing at a time. In any case, we can’t do anything till we get home. Let’s forget it all till then.”

And I stooped down and got a mackerel line from the locker, and showed her how to reel it out, but she was listless and depressed. We caught a couple close off Berry Head, but she was still distrait; I silenced the flutter of the fish and cursed myself that we had gone ashore at all. Better, I thought, if we had been content to look at Torquay from the sea, and so we rounded Berry Head and bore away for home.

It was seven o’clock by the time we were back at moorings off my yard. We came to them under power; to save time I had got the main down as we passed the Battery. I made all square and got the dinghy up, and sculled ashore with Mollie to the steps. In silence we drove up together through the town; I sent her up to change when we got in, and went and had a bath myself before we dined.

It was a little difficult at dinner with the servants there. I forget what we talked about; I only remember that Mollie was restless and uncomfortable. I fancy that I must have sat there talking at her easily, a steady, even flow of meaningless conversation about ships and harbours while I thought of other things. I could not make up my mind whether to let Fedden know at once about this new development, as I should have done. I was sick of the police and their ways. Moreover, I had no idea how far her brother might be implicated in this thing. It would certainly be better if he had a talk with Jenkinson before the police got hold of him.

It was a cloudless summer evening. We finished our dessert and went out on to the terrace, looking out over the Range. Rogers brought out our coffee there, and then we were alone, and I could come straight to the point that we wanted to discuss. “This girl Edna,” I remarked, and she looked up quickly at me. “Do you know where she lives? Could you take me to her, for example?”

She nodded. “It’s in Hammersmith, not far from the Palais, the one they call Dreamland. She lives with her mother, that keeps a sweet shop in Auburn Road. Just where the Fulham Palace Road goes off, like.”

“Do you think she’d know where Billy is?”

“Oh, yes. You see, he’s always writing to her, because he told me.” She frowned a little. “I think she’s ever so silly,” she said impatiently.

I stood there, silent for a little, smoking my cigar and staring out over the harbour mouth. If I went to Fedden with this information it was probable that the police would get to Billy first, before I could. I owed it to the girl to see that her brother got the best chance that he could have with the law, and after the affair at Newton Abbot I had no confidence whatever in the integrity of Fedden and the CID. It seemed likely to me that if they got to Billy first he would be allowed to commit himself to God knows what, in ignorance that there were solicitors and barristers engaged for his defence and guidance. That could not be allowed.

The other course would be to go and find him for myself, take him to Jenkinson, and then present him to the police with Jenkinson to hold his hand. That might be the better way, but it would mean the father and mother of a row with Fedden….

I turned to her at last. “My dear,” I said, “I think we ought to go to town and have a talk with this girl.”

“You mean we ought to try and find Billy?” she inquired. “I’m sure she’d know, because he writes to her, you see.” She paused. “Would that be the best thing for him?”

“I think so,” I replied. “I think we can probably help him.”

She said, a little hesitantly: “I was thinking we might just forget, and pretend I hadn’t told you about Edna.” She raised her eyes to mine. “Wouldn’t that do as well?”

I considered for a moment. There was a great deal to be said for that line of action, but I couldn’t see that it would come out right. “The police are sure to find him in the end,” I said. “It can be only a matter of a few days now before he’s caught. I think we’d better find him ourselves first, and get him into touch with Jenkinson.”

She sighed. “I know he wouldn’t be doing anything wrong, not really.” And then she said: “Will we be going up to London, then?”

“I think so,” I replied. “I think we’d better go tomorrow.”

There was a little pause. “Just you and me?” she asked. “Staying together in a hotel, or something of that?”

I met her eye, and laughed shortly. “That’s right,” I said. “In two separate rooms. Two hotels, if you like.”

To my astonishment, she blushed at what I said. I stood and watched the slow colour creep from her face down her neck towards her shoulders, and she looked down and made a little pattern in the dust upon the terrace parapet. “I wouldn’t want that,” she said quietly. “Two rooms is good enough.”

I sheered off what seemed to be an unexpectedly difficult subject for her, and we went walking down the garden in the evening light. She had come to know each flower in my garden intimately, as from the bud; I think my garden was the greatest pleasure that she had during the time she stayed with me. We strolled round in the dusk and picked a few roses for her room, till she was tired and ready for her bed. “I do get sleepy ever so quick here,” she said. She stood and looked around the hills and sea, dim and already cradled in the night. “It’s quiet here, and nice….”

I went with her to the open windows of the library, and paused upon the threshold as she went inside. “Good night, Mollie,” I said quietly.

She paused inside the window, half a yard from me. “Goodnight, Malcolm dear,” she said. “It’s been ever such a lovely day. I think it’s been the loveliest I’ve ever had.” And so she passed into the shadows of the room, and I was left alone to smoke a cigarette before I, too, went up to bed. I slept quite well, those days.

We went to town next day by train from Exeter. I knew very little of hotels in London; it must have been some fifteen years since I stayed in one. I have my club, and that is all that I have ever needed there. I took her to one of those enormous, modernistic palaces, all glass and stainless steel, that are springing up all over the West End; we had a couple of adjoining rooms there on the third floor, and paid a pretty penny for them. I hated the place right from the very first, but everything was new to her.

“It’s awfully nice,” she breathed. “It’s like the Regal Palace in Manchester, only much grander.”

We got there in the middle of the afternoon. She told me that Edna did not leave work till six o’clock; if we called at the sweetshop at about half past six we stood a good chance of finding her. We had our tea uncomfortably in the painted lounge, while the band played somewhere out of sight and one or two couples danced languidly in the hot air on an enormous floor. I sipped the unpleasant beverage they served as tea, and wished very much that I was in my club.

And presently we went to Hammersmith. We got there on top of a bus from Piccadilly; at Hammersmith Broadway we got off, and Sixpence took me walking for some way down the hot pavements till she stopped in front of a little sweetshop and tobacconist.

“This is it,” she said, and we went in.

There was no one in the shop. It was small, and not very well stocked, with a tobacco counter on one side and a sweet counter on the other. In the back wall there was a door with a glass window in the upper half of it; through the lace curtain one could see a sitting–room, and people at the table. One of them got up and opened the door, and a fat untidy woman came out into the shop and looked at us inquiringly.

“Good evening, Mrs Tinsey,” said Mollie. “I came to see if Edna was here.”

The fat woman peered at her for a moment, and then raised her hands. “Well,” she said, “if it isn’t Mary Gordon!” She raised her voice. “Edna,” she cried. “Edna … here’s Mary Gordon come.”

From the back room there came a girl with fair, wavy hair, bobbed, dressed in a white blouse and a dark skirt; a girl with rather a determined look about her—Billy’s girl. “Oh, my dear!” she said to Mollie, and ran at her and kissed her. “After all this time! Just fancy!”

Mollie disengaged herself and turned to me. “Edna,” she said. “This is my friend.” I murmured something that I thought was suitable, and Edna said: “Pleased, I’m sure.”

We went through with them into the back room. It was chock full of rather old and inexpensive furniture, and the table was laid for a meal. In the grate I saw the teapot stewing down before the fire; the kipper bones and cherry cake were still upon the table. We put aside their hospitality with some difficulty by assuring them that we had had our tea; I remember in particular that Mother was urgent to ‘run out and get another kipper—it wouldn’t take but a moment’. We compounded with them in the end by drinking cups of the stewed tea with cigarettes—‘stock, my dear’—and I sat and made conversation with Mother about the state of trade, particularly the sweetshop trade, while the girls talked. I gathered from the things I overheard that they had been together in a Palais somewhere in the south. I think that probably Edna had been an amateur and a habitué of some Palais where my girl had worked.

The door bell rang, and Mother rose and went out into the shop to serve a customer. As soon as she had gone, Mollie got straight to the business we had come upon. “Say, Edna,” she inquired. “Have you heard anything from Billy the last few weeks?” She paused. “I mean, that you’d be able to tell me his address?”

Edna nodded. “I got a letter from him somewhere.” She rose, and went hunting in a littered sort of escritoire in a corner of the room. Finally she produced a little sheaf of letters from a drawer and opened one. I saw Mollie looking at her keenly—so she kept his letters, anyway.

“Gloucester,” she said. “That’s the last. Maybe it’d be three weeks back.” She looked at the others. “The one before that was there, and the one before that. The one before that was Birmingham, but that was Christmas, that one.”

She glanced at Sixpence. “I’d say he was still at Gloucester with the lorry, because he said he was working from there, like.” She turned over the letter—“16 Smallpiece Lane was where he wrote from.”

I made a note of the address. “You didn’t see him lately?” asked Mollie.

The other girl considered for a moment. “He come here one evening last month, maybe six weeks back. It was the night after the fire at Pinsons, because I remember.”

Mollie persisted. “You haven’t seen him since, not to speak to?”

The other shook her head. “It ain’t no good him coming here,” she said quietly. “I told him that.”

There was a silence after that. In the shop the bell was ringing intermittently; a string of customers was passing in and out. “It didn’t ought to be like that,” said Mollie slowly. She glanced up at the other girl. “Wouldn’t it be any good—not ever? I mean, there never was any other person for Billy, not like some.”

I moved a little way away, so far as one could do so in that narrow room, and peered out through the curtain of the door that led in to the shop. Behind me I heard Edna say: “It ain’t no good. Seems like he’s not the man for me, Mollie. It isn’t that I want a Valentino, or anything of that. Billy’s all right. But it’d have to be just right for me to marry anyone, and it wouldn’t be just right with Billy—see? I’d rather go on working at Slimlines. Maybe you think I’m silly over it.”

Mollie said: “Oh … I don’t know.”

Edna pursued her point. “You wouldn’t ever take a chap unless it was just right, yourself.”

No reply came to that one, I remember; instead, there came a little awkward pause. I turned back to the room. “It looks as if we’ll have to go on down to Gloucester,” I said easily. “We can go down there tomorrow and hunt him up.”

“That’s right,” said Edna, “16 Smallpiece Lane. That was where he wrote from last time. I reckon he’s still there, maybe.”

There was nothing left for us to stay for, then. We made our farewells and got out into the street after some time. When we were out of sight I hailed a taxi, and we went driving round the Park till dinnertime, talking of Billy and the people that we saw in the street. I must say Mollie seemed to be more interested in the latter. This was a holiday to her, and she was out to get the last ounce out of it.

We dined that night in the hotel, and danced a little afterwards to a good band. Then we went to bed, both tired with the day.

Next morning we went down to Gloucester. We lunched there, in the best hotel that I could find, and after lunch went on to look for Smallpiece Lane. It proved to be a shabby little row of urban houses on the outskirts of the town, that ran out and ended in a field, a pasture with worn earth patches where the children of the neighbourhood had played. We found the house and knocked; the door was opened by a thin, gaunt woman in an apron.

“Is Mr Gordon in?” I asked.

“In the garidge,” she replied. “You’ll find him in the garidge.”

“Where is that?” I asked.

It was about two streets away; we went on there at once. It proved to be a sort of yard behind a pair of open double gates, a place with an oily, earthen floor and a tumble–down shed at one end of it. The doors of this shed was open, and I saw the stem end of a lorry sticking out, and an old Morris car.

We passed in at the gates, and crossed the yard towards the shed. There was a man working on the engine of the lorry; at the sound of our footsteps he straightened up and looked at us.

“Billy,” cried Molly. “Bill–ee….”

He was a stocky, pleasant–looking chap, not very tall. A shock of reddish hair hung over his blue eyes; he was very dirty from his work. He wore a soiled blue suit, torn at the back and greasy on the knees with oil and mud. He came towards us, smiling and wiping his hands upon a bit of rag.

“’Ullo!” he said. “And what brought you down here, girl? This isn’t half a surprise!”

I glanced at Sixpence, and she was glowing with pleasure. This brother meant a lot to her. “Oh, Billy, this is nice,” she said.

“Well, well, well, well, well,” he replied succinctly. “Not half, it isn’t. But what brings you to Gloucester?”

She said: “We wanted to find you, Billy.” And then she added: “Oh, Billy, this is my friend, Commander Stevenson.”

I put out a hand; he rubbed his own with his rag, and shook it genially. “Pleased to meet you, sir,” he said. “Any friend of Mollie’s….”

The words died down upon his lips; I saw the laughter go out of his eyes as he stood looking into my face. He let go my hand and stood there staring at me, open mouthed; I stood and watched the colour drain out of his face, and watched the apprehension creep into his eyes. In fifteen seconds he had changed into a different man. “Strewth … ” he said quietly, so quietly that I hardly heard what he had said.

Mollie said: “Billy … whatever is the matter?”

He pulled himself together. “Matter?” he said sharply. “Nothing’s the matter. What d’you think?”

She stared at him. “You look as if you’d seen a ghost. Honest, you do.”

He forced a smile. “I did get a bit of a turn. Your friend, he’s just the image of a man I met one time.” He laughed uneasily. “Funny, them turns one gets….”

I had been thinking quickly, studying the weatherbeaten face, the shock of red, untidy hair, the friendly blue eyes. I had never seen this man before, but that might not be necessary. I smiled, and stood staring straight at him. “Maybe you’ve seen me somewhere before,” I said amicably. “Down Dartmouth way, perhaps.” I was watching closely, and I saw him blink. “I drive a Bentley Six saloon.”

The colour had all gone from his face. “No,” he said at last. “I never seen you before.” A child could have told that he was lying. He turned suddenly on Mollie. “Here, girl,” he cried; “who is this bloke, and where does he come from? What is he to you, eh?”

She pressed my arm. “Billy,” she said, a little hurt, “you didn’t ought to speak like that. This is my friend.”

I stood there smiling at him grimly, still staring him in the face. “I was able to help your sister when she got into a bit of trouble,” I explained, “with the police. They found a burning motor lorry, and they thought she might know who the driver was.”

There was a long, awkward silence after I said that. In the distance I heard the children playing in the street outside, and the long clanking of an engine shunting in some siding near at hand. He stood there like a naughty schoolboy, looking down and scraping the earth with the toe of his boot. “You’re to do with the police?” he inquired.

I shook my head. “Not me.”

“Billy,” said Mollie, “he isn’t with the police. He was ever so good when I was in the station, and stopped them, and got a lawyer all the way from London, and everything. Honest, he did.”

I wondered if that sentence was comprehensible to him. I doubt it, for he raised his head sullenly, with an ugly flush. “Then if he’s not from the police, what the hell does he want here? I do my business, and don’t worry nobody.”

“What is your business, anyway?” I asked.

“Lorrying,” he said defiantly. “Now you clear out o’ this. I’ve had enough of you. I’ve got my work to do.”

Sixpence said: “But, Billy…. You can’t just push us out like that.”

“Cheese it, girl,” he retorted, not unkindly. “You buzz off now, and I’ll write to you.”

I moved to the Morris Cowley and sat down upon the running board, my elbow resting on my knees. “The police have got your lorry,” I remarked, “—the one that was burnt out. They know the number plates were false. They found the three carpet sweepers that you left behind, two burnt up in the lorry, and one behind the hedge. They’re looking for you all over the country. They’ll have got your description by this time.” I paused reflectively. “It was a good game, but it’s finished now.”

There was another long, uneasy silence. He stood there shuffling a little with his feet, and shooting furtive glances at me as I sat there on the running board. “I don’t see who you are,” he said at last.

I tried a long shot. “I’m the fellow who was in the car,” I said.

“Oh, chuck fooling,” he said irritably. “I know that.” He was silent for a minute, and then he said: “What I want to know is—what’s the game?”

Mollie was standing silent a little way away from us, and leaving the whole thing to me. I sat there for a minute staring out across the littered, oily yard, watching the smoke from a bonfire in a rubbish pit curling lazily up into a light blue, summer sky. My long shot had gone home all right. “There’s no game,” I replied. “No game at all.”

I glanced up at him, standing over me. “When you left that lorry burning on the road, the police were after you like a knife. They couldn’t find you, but they got to know that Miss Gordon was your sister, and they took her down to Dartmouth to question her about you. I came in then, and got a lawyer to look after her.”

“That’s right, Billy,” put in Sixpence eagerly. “And all the way from London, too. It was ever so good of the Commander.”

I smiled a little, wondering idly where she had picked that up. Only the servants call me the Commander and the men down at the yard. She must have picked it up from Rogers or one of the maids…. Then I came back to earth.

I met his eyes. “I’m here to tell you that the police are looking for you now,” I said. “You haven’t got a chance. You can’t even get out of the country, now. If you stay here they’ll get you in a day or two. And if you run, they’ll get you in a week.”

He burst out: “But I ain’t done nothing!” He stared at me. “Nothing, save lorrying for them, and leaving me lorry on the road. Them things aren’t crimes—they can’t do nothing to you for that. What do they want with me?”

I motioned him to the step of the lorry opposite me. “Sit down,” I said. “There’s no sense standing up all day.” And Mollie came and sat beside me on the Cowley running board, and I said:

“They want you because they want the other lot. They can’t find out anything about them—yet—but they’ll get you all right.”

He repeated sullenly: “I ain’t done nothing wrong….”

Sixpence stirred irritably beside me. “Don’t act so soft,” she said. “The Commander’s all for us, not for the police or anyone. Why don’t you tell him what’s been going on?”

He looked a little foolish, laughed, and pushed back his cap to scratch his head with an oily hand. “Reckon he knows most of it,” he said, embarrassed.

“I’d like to hear what happened when we met before,” I remarked.

And cutting short his tale, it came to this. He had picked up two foreigners near Newton Abbot by an assignation, and had driven on down to Dartmouth with them in the empty lorry. They arrived on the shore road at about one o’clock in the morning and stopped a few hundred yards up the road from the corner where my car was subsequently found, towards the town. From there his companions made their signal to the sea and got the reply. His two companions then went down to the shore, and Gordon stayed by his lorry. He had no part in handling the cargo.

About half an hour later the two foreigners came back, carrying the first case; behind them came two men from the ship, carrying another one. One of these men was a young Englishman that he had seen before on these occasions; he thought that he had to do with the vessel that they used.

It was at that point that the car appeared.

They saw the headlights on the road two or three miles away; it was clear to them that the car was being driven very fast. As a precautionary measure they covered up the cases in the lorry, two of them got inside, and Gordon lifted the bonnet as if with engine trouble. But the car stopped short of them. They heard it come along at a great pace, and in the still night they heard the squeal of brakes as it drew up a quarter of a mile away. Then the headlights stopped motionless upon the road, and they stood staring at each other in consternation.

Presently two of the men detached themselves, got over into the fields, and made a wide circuit in the darkness towards the strange car to investigate. Gordon stood waiting by his lorry; after a time the Englishman slipped off and went direct down to the beach.

That was all he saw, but he told me what had happened. “When they got close they seen a man walking from the car down to the beach,” he said. “Walking quiet like, over the grass, he was.” They went close enough to the car to see that there was nobody else there, and then they followed on the stranger’s heels down to the beach. “They took him for a coastguard of some sort. They come up behind him down there somewhere, and slugged him proper,” he explained. “With a pistol, with the handle, like.”

I felt Mollie stir beside me, and I smiled. “That’s right,” I said. I paused a minute, and inquired: “What happened then?”

He laughed. “They weren’t half in a stew.” The next thing he knew was that they came up from the beach to the lorry, all three of them, together with a girl. He had not seen the girl before; he thought that she must have come upon the boat. They were carrying what seemed to be a corpse, and in the party there were bitter words passing. At the lorry they laid the body down and the girl at once began attending to it, removing and renewing a rough, bloodstained bandage on the head. The man was quite unconscious.

They stood there for some time wrangling over what was to be done, and then they went off to view the car up the road, still arguing as they went. And by the time they got there it had begun to dawn on them that there was no significance at all in what had happened at the beach; the man was quite alone, and he was very drunk. Actually, there had been no necessity to strike him down at all; if they had humoured him he would have gone away and would have forgotten the whole thing next day. But there he was, drunk and unconscious, and with a serious head injury. A well–dressed fellow, too—possibly somebody of importance.

They’d got themselves into a pretty mess.

It was the young Englishman who suggested that they should stage a motor crash. He argued, rather forcibly, that the fellow was so drunk that he’d probably have piled his car up anyway before he reached his home, and that it was just as likely to have happened here as anywhere. Nobody had any better solution to their difficulty to suggest, and so they set about it.

Gordon drove the car a hundred yards along the road to the corner and transversely into the ditch in skidding attitude. With the assistance of a crowbar they contrived to turn it over on its side into the hedge—a big job, for it was a heavy car. They went round it with the crowbar then, breaking the glass and damaging the wings, but it was the young Englishman who thought of kicking through the roof above the driver’s seat. They did the best they could. Taking it all round, I think they must have made a rotten job of it; if any serious inquiry had been made it must have been obvious at once that was no real crash. But no inquiry of that sort was necessary, I suppose. The fellow’s habits were well known.

And finally they brought along the body and laid it in the car. The man was still breathing heavily, and the bleeding from the scalp had stopped. The girl insisted that the position should be such that the head was raised a little, and they had some difficulty over this.

So they finished the unloading of the boat and came away. The man was still in a deep coma when they left, and it was close on dawn. They found out two days later that he had been found a couple of hours afterwards; he was in a nursing home and likely to get over it. It seemed a very satisfactory solution to what might have been a nasty incident.

Gordon laughed, a little ruefully. “They wasn’t half pleased when they heard that,” he said. “Well out of it, they thought they was….”

I nodded slowly. “Would you recognise the man again?”

There was a little silence in the yard. He hesitated, and then said: “I would, sir. It was you.”

“Yes,” I said absently, “I suppose it was.” I was thinking of the further links I wanted to get out of him and for the moment I was silent, till I said:

“How did that lorry come to go on fire?”

He was annoyed. “Silliest thing you ever saw,” he said. “I never seen such!” He glanced at me, irrepressible. “But coo! she didn’t half flare up! Filling up, it was. I’d got the filler off the tank and pouring in from the can, and another can unstoppered beside me. An’ then one of them went to light a fag.” He laughed. “She went off with such a puff I fell backwards off the running board into the road, an’ dropped the can and petrol over everything. You never seen such a mess! They fellows was out of the back like a knife and there she was. We just couldn’t do anything with her.”

I wrinkled my brows. “You had a load on board?” I asked. “I suppose it happened after you’d left the boat?”

“Oh, aye,” he said. “We got the most of it off her before it got too bad—all the cartridges and that, but some of the stuff we had to leave. I had the little Morris with me that trip”—he indicated the car beside us—“and we piled it all into her till she was down on her springs. Then she was full, an’ still a case or two left, an’ we put them down behind the hedge and went on in the Morris. But I reckon they must have been found, because they was gone next day. Still, I don’t see what else we could have done….”

I asked him where the stuff was going to, and to my surprise he told me readily. He took it to Trepwll in Breconshire, about thirty miles north of Cardiff. That was a run of about a hundred and sixty miles, which usually took ten hours or so. His garage in Gloucester was handy for this run, and he eked out the business of these journeys with a certain amount of local work of various descriptions.

He told me that in all he had made five trips. I had blundered into the second landing, and his lorry had been burnt upon the last. The lorry that he had now was another one, which he had purchased second–hand as a replacement. He was overhauling it for the next journey.

“When is that?” I asked.

He did not know. It would be in about a week’s time; he only got two days’ notice of each trip. They paid him forty pounds a trip—not bad, he said, for twenty–four hours’ work. For this he promised secrecy.

He deposited his loads at a farm about two miles from Trepwll. Sometimes he had passengers upon these journeys and these were mostly foreigners; once he had gone alone. He did not know the names of any of the men that he had met, and he had resolutely kept his eyes shut upon the nature of the business. He was content to obey orders while things went well; in the event of any trouble he would look after himself, and get out of it as best he could. He got his orders from a man that he knew as Mr Palmer, who came to him personally before each trip.

That was the substance of the tale he had to tell. I liked the man, I must say; if he was a rogue he was a cheerful one. To him the whole affair had been a matter of business and no more; he had made good money, and he wasn’t one to worry about ethics. He seemed to have no knowledge of the purpose of the guns, or interest. In fact, he told me that he had not known the nature of his cargoes till the lorry was burnt out, but it made no difference when he did discover it. His business was lorrying.

“Your next trip’s in about a week’s time, then?” I asked.

“That’s right, sir,” he replied. He sat there musing for a minute. “I don’t know as I’ll go on that one now. I don’t want to get mixed up with no police….”

Mollie said; “Oh, Billy, you might have thought of that before!”

He looked up at her, and grinned, a little sheepishly. “Strewth,” he said, “I never thought of it like that.”

It seemed to me that there was information here that Fedden and his policemen ought to have, and that I could not allow this thing to be suppressed. I was equally certain that Jenkinson should be with this man when he made his statement to the police. As far as I could see it, the extent of his wrong–doing would be well covered by a ten–bob fine; they might not take that view of things at Scotland Yard. Jenkinson must be there. I sat and thought about it for a minute, till at last I said:

“The police will be here any day now—you’ll have to be prepared for that. You’ll have to tell them all that you’ve told me.”

He shifted uneasily. “That’s no way to go on. I got good money to keep my mouth shut.” And then he burst out again: “I ain’t done nothing!”

It was Mollie who replied to that. “Oh, don’t keep on like that,” she said impatiently. “You been smuggling guns into the country, that’s what you been doing, like the Commander says. It’s no good you kidding yourself that way.”

He scratched his head unhappily. “I dunno what to do,” he said.

It took about an hour’s hard talking to persuade him that our course was best. But we left that night for London, all the three of us, and by ten o’clock next morning I had him closeted with Jenkinson.

Chapter 10

I don’t think I need go through in detail the examination which was made of Billy in London. I got him in to Jenkinson, and when we had satisfied ourselves that he could tell us no more than he had told me at Gloucester, we sent for Norman. I had the pleasure of ringing up that gentleman myself, from Jenkinson’s office.

I got on to him at Scotland Yard. “This is Commander Stevenson this end,” I said. “Is that Major Norman?”

“Speaking,” he replied.

“Good morning,” I said courteously. “I’m speaking from Mr Jenkinson’s office—you’ve met Mr Jenkinson, haven’t you? Oh, yes, I was forgetting. We’ve got a young chap here that you might like to have a word or two with—I should say, that Mr Jenkinson sees no objection. The driver of the lorry. What? Yes, the driver of the lorry that was burnt out. Miss Gordon’s brother.”

He burst out: “You say you’ve got him in your office? How long have you had him there?”

“Oh … let’s see, now,” I replied. “I saw him first in Gloucester yesterday, and brought him up last night. We’ve examined what he has to say, and there really seems to be no reason why he shouldn’t make a statement to you, if it would help you in your work in any way. Mr Jenkinson will be present all the time, of course, to guard his interests.”

He said angrily: “See here, Mr Stevenson, if that man gets away I shall hold you responsible for his escape.”

“Certainly,” I said. “Do I understand that you would like to see him? If so, I’ll ask him to wait here for a few minutes.”

“I’ll be round right now,” he said.

“Oh, that’s excellent,” I said pleasantly. “In about a quarter of an hour’s time? I think that will be quite convenient for him.”

I didn’t get an answer to that one. The line was suddenly cut off; I think he must have been in something of a hurry.

He came in a remarkably short time, and with him was a shorthand man. He was inclined to be a little curt with me, so far as I remember—I can’t imagine why. We went through into a sort of Board Room next door to Jenkinson’s office, and sat down round a table while Norman asked his questions.

There was nothing new. He didn’t know any more than he had told me. Norman pressed him particularly upon the source of his instructions, but he knew nothing other than that the man he knew as Palmer turned up at Gloucester at his garage or his lodgings from time to time and left messages for him. It was from this man that he got his money after each trip, forty pounds in treasury notes. He had no means of finding him at other times. On the morning of each trip the man turned up at the garage and travelled down with him upon the lorry.

He gave a pretty full description of this man, but there was precious little in it to take hold of. He described a man of forty–five or fifty years of age, with grey hair and rather refined speech.

For the destination of his loads, however, he was able to supply clear evidence. He took the stuff to a farmhouse in Breconshire, not far from Trepwll; at this place it was unloaded and carried into a barn. He could identify this farm clearly, though he did not know its name. He gave such positive directions as to how you reached it from Trepwll as would identify it beyond all doubt.

The statement came to an end at last. Norman sent away his stenographer to get it typed, and it was arranged that Jenkinson should take Gordon down that afternoon to Scotland Yard to go over it and sign his deposition. Norman departed then, and I took Mollie and her brother out to lunch, at Mr Lyons’ Corner House.

We took him back to Jenkinson at about three o’clock; together they went off to Scotland Yard. Mollie and I took a taxi back to the hotel. She was tired, and a little bewildered by the events of the day.

“I do think it’s awful to get mixed up with the police,” she said. She had a wholesome dread of the constabulary.

I got a telephone message late that afternoon, summoning me to Sir David Carter at 10.30 the next morning. I wondered who was going to be there. I didn’t see what they wanted me for; if ever I was resolved upon one thing it was that I was taking no more part in police affairs. I’d had my fill of that; from this time onwards I was going to devote myself merely to the protection of Mollie and her brother against their irregularities.

Gordon turned up soon after tea; little of any consequence had happened at the Yard. I gave him over to Mollie for the evening, saw that they had plenty of money, and left them to their own devices; I judged that they would talk more freely if I were away. I dined that evening at the club, and took a hand of bridge. By the time that I got back to the hotel they had gone up to bed.

Mollie opened the door as I went into my room; her room was next to mine. She was wearing a kimono and her hair was down her back; in the dim light of the passage she seemed to me to be most beautiful. “I’m glad you’re back,” she said, a little oddly. “Billy and I, we had a lovely time. We went to the pictures. But it’s dreadfully expensive here.”

I smiled. “I had a bit of an expensive evening, too,” I said. “I was playing cards.”

“You wouldn’t like a cup of tea, or a whisky or anything like that, would you?” she asked. “I mean, I’ll put on my frock, and we’ll get a waiter if you like.”

“Don’t worry about the frock,” I said. “You’re much nicer like that.”

She coloured a little, and told me not to be so awful.

“No, I don’t want anything,” I said. “Just bed.”

There was a little pause.

“Goodnight, Commander Stevenson,” she said.

“Goodnight, Mollie,” I replied, and went into my room.

Next day I went down to the Yard and saw Sir David Carter. Norman was with him in his room, and Fedden; they must have got him up from Dartmouth in a hurry. They offered me a chair at a long table; Sir David left his desk, and he settled to a sort of conference.

He started off: “I should like to begin by offering my thanks, Commander Stevenson, for the services which you have rendered in this business. Colonel Fedden and Major Norman tell me that we owe a great deal to you, in securing the evidence of the young woman Gordon, and of her brother. I should like you to feel that we appreciate your help.”

I had come prepared to hold my own in any bickering, but this old man had rather spiked my guns. “I’m interested in those two,” I said at last. “They’re a good type, and I’d like to see them clear of any trouble.”

He inclined his head. “Exactly so. I hope sincerely that it will not be necessary for us to make any trouble for them. At the moment we do not anticipate that sort of difficulty.”

“I’m glad to hear it,” I replied. “After what I’ve seen I should defend them with all the resources in my power,” and I glanced from the old man to Norman on his other side.

Sir David Carter coughed. “Leaving that aspect of the matter for the moment,” he said, “I thought it would perhaps be best to send for you, Commander Stevenson, before we communicate our proposals to the man, William Gordon. Major Norman informs me that you have considerable influence with both of them; as the procedure which we have decided on is of some delicacy, I think it right that we should put it to you first.”

I thrust my chair back from the table. “See here,” I said; “I’m out of this. I’m sorry, but I can’t do any more for you.”

There was a little pause. “Nevertheless,” remarked Sir David, “I should like you to hear what we propose.”

I relaxed my attitude. “I should be very glad to,” I replied. “But I can take no part in any of your plans.”

He nodded. “We should not wish you to.”

He picked up a pen holder from the tray before him and began playing with it absently, a favourite trick of his. “You will have gathered the position for yourself,” he said. “We now know the destination of the guns, and a great deal more about the manner in which they are introduced into the country. We do not know the organisers of the enterprise. We do not know the nature of the ship that brings them, though the evidence of Sir Philip Stenning throws a little light on that. We do know that the guns are taken to Trepwll, and from that we can deduce, without a great deal of investigation, who they are intended for.”

He raised his head and looked at me. “There is trouble in that district, as you know.”

I did know. It was not far from the Glanferis mines, and the Conservative papers had been full of the Glanferis troubles for the last three months. The coal trouble had virtually closed the pits, and there was much labour unrest. There had been riots and isolated policemen had been beaten up; the papers put this down to Communist incitement. On the eve of the election, with the poll not five weeks off, Glanferis had assumed a disproportionate importance; its new value had been sedulously worked up. Glanferis was a front–page story at that time.

The old man was staring straight at me, still playing with his pen. “I want you to visualise the whole situation, to see it from the broadest point of view. If we go straight now to Trepwll we shall find arms. In that event, we might be forced to the incredible conclusion that the Welsh miners in that district are preparing for an armed revolt against the Crown.”

I met his eyes. “You find that quite incredible?” I asked.

“Absolutely,” he said quietly.

Norman broke in. “We have the most complete reports upon the situation in Glanferis,” he remarked. “This comes as a complete surprise. We cannot imagine what section of the disputants could find it to their interest to arm their men. The use of force against the Crown cuts clean across the policy of every party in that district. It would mean political disaster for the party that attempted it. It’s inconceivable.”

“Still,” I said, “there the guns are. You can’t get away from that.”

Sir David sighed. “Yes, there they are.” I was a little sorry for him in his great responsibility.

He pursued his discourse. “I am taking it upon myself to delay the seizure of those guns,” he said quietly. “I would not have you think that we are shirking from our duty on account of the election, for fear of the effect that may be produced upon the electorate if guns should be discovered in Glanferis. We are rather concerned to ensure that when the matter is made public for the first time, the whole story shall be quite complete. I would not bring it out in bits and pieces. I want the directing intelligence behind those guns. I want evidence which will show for what reason they are there—in comparison with that evidence the guns are nothing.” He turned to me. “This country stands on the eve of a poll, Commander Stevenson. We seem to be in the unfortunate position of having to produce a bombshell for the public, another Zinovieff letter which may change the whole course of the election. If we have to do that we must have solid facts behind us—not merely guns and theories as to what they were intended for. The public must be told the truth of this affair if it be told anything at all.”

“I’m with you there,” I said. “Give the country the whole truth of whatever may be going on, and let it do what it thinks best. It won’t go wrong.”

He inclined his head. “Exactly so.”

Fedden stirred. “That leads us to the man Gordon,” he said. It was the first time he had spoken.

I raised my eyebrows. “How does he come into it?”

Sir David Carter said: “We propose to use him for the next few days for information purposes.”

I was about to speak, but he stopped me. “I will tell you first what we propose. We shall send him back to his work at Gloucester, keeping him quietly under observation there. We shall give him to understand that no proceedings will be taken for the slight irregularities of which he may be guilty, on the condition that he supplies us with the information that we want. We want the man Palmer, primarily. Next, we want information about the next landing of arms to enable us to make a capture of the boat. Given those two, I think we shall secure sufficient evidence for us to put the matter to the public for its judgment.”

He paused. “I would not have you think that we enjoy these methods that we have to use,” he said a little sternly, looking straight at me. “Our business is to catch criminals, and to find out the truth.”

I nodded. “I appreciate that point.”

I sat and thought about it for a minute, and there was a silence in the room. Their attitude was reasonable; it was the only way to get the information quickly that would settle this affair. Billy must go back to Gloucester and deliver the man Palmer over to the police.

I saw now why they wanted me. They were no fools, and they knew that I had influence with Mollie. They could not make the man go back to Gloucester if he did not want to; they could not make him betray his associates. They were relying on Mollie and myself to influence him that that would be the right thing to do; they must have seen that threats would be of no avail. There was good stuff in that chap.

I could not deny that they were right, nor could I deny them help. The matter was too serious for that. Against my will they’d got me into it again.

I raised my head. “And you want me to do … what?”

It was exactly as I had thought. They had not seen Gordon or put this thing to him; they wanted me to do that. They wanted me to represent to him that the police were his friends, only anxious to help him in his difficulties and to guide him out of the mess that he had got into. I was to have a quiet talk with him with Mollie, and then to take him along and introduce him to one or two plain–clothes men the next day. Then he was to go back to Gloucester, and wait for developments.

“There isn’t any danger in it,” Norman said. “I can assure you that it’s a procedure which is often used.”

I stared at him. “I am quite ready to believe it,” I remarked, a little grimly.

I turned to Carter. “I will see what I can do,” I said. “You understand that I can promise nothing—nothing whatsoever. I’ll put it to them, and I’ll telephone to you this afternoon.”

I left the Yard and went back to the hotel. Mollie was out somewhere with her brother—shopping, I suppose. I waited in the lounge for them. They came in presently and we had lunch, and after lunch I took them up into my bedroom for our talk.

I put it to them as fairly as I could. I told them all that I had heard at Scotland Yard, and I told them what the police wanted to find out. I explained as clearly as I could the political reasons underlying the whole thing; I think that Billy understood that more than Mollie did. He was accustomed to reading newspapers. I told them, frankly, that I thought they ought to help; that what the police were asking was a reasonable thing. In his small way Billy had helped to get the country into some sort of a mess, and it was up to him to help to get it out again.

“I dunno what to say,” he said. “It don’t seem right to me … .”

But Mollie broke in there. “Don’t act so soft,” she said. “The Commander knows what’s best….”

Eventually we all went round to Jenkinson, and put the thing to him. He could not help us very much, beyond the general advice that where the police demands were reasonable they should be met so far as possible. He was inclined to think that their demands were reasonable now, and that our best course was to fall in with their plans.

So we agreed, and Billy was content to go. I rang up Norman and arranged for Billy to visit Scotland Yard that afternoon, and to go down to Gloucester that same evening; it was obviously desirable that he should get back there as soon as possible. Mollie and I escorted him to Scotland Yard and said goodbye to him; he was diffident and uneasy in his new rôle. I was uneasy, too, but I could see no other way of handling the situation.

I arranged with him that I would take his sister back to Dartmouth and we would wait there till this affair was over. As soon as he was free he would come down to us there.

And so we left him, and went back to the hotel.

Mollie was absent minded and uneasy all that night. We dressed and dined, and I took her out to a revue; she enjoyed it, but her mind was never very far away from Billy. She kept on asking little, difficult questions of the work that we had sent him on—was it often done that way, and was it ever dangerous? I answered these to the best of my ability and reassured her, I suppose; I wish I could have reassured myself. Not one of our better evenings, taking all in all, and I was glad to go to bed.

We took a morning train to Exeter next day, and Adams met us with the car. I drove and Adams sat behind; it was a warm and sunny afternoon. As we got on the road our spirits rose: the Yard seemed very far away from Devonshire that day. We went down through Newton Abbot and Totnes, with Mollie lighting cigarettes for me, and marvelling at the automatic lighter as it glowed.

We got to Dartmouth just in time for tea; it was good to be back home again. I don’t like London, and though one goes up there from time to time on business or for boredom, I am always best pleased with my own place, with the sea and with my work. This afternoon as we sat having tea together in the library, with Mollie prattling away of the things that she had done and things that she would like to do in London, I remember thinking what a very good place home was.

And I remember thinking what a dreary place my home had been before the girl had come to stay with me. I remember wondering what I should do when this was over and she went away.

We went down into the garden after tea and picked some roses for her room; she loved her flowers. And then we went a little way down the fuzzy, till we stopped where I had had a seat put up, and we sat there in the evening sun while I smoked a pipe, looking out over the Range and the wide sea. And as we sat there a vessel came into sight from the west, a little cutter under all plain sail, making for the Range and Dartmouth on the evening flood.

“Hullo,” I said, and pointed with my pipe. “There’s Stenning.”

It was only four days since we sailed together, but it seemed much more to us. Stenning had been on a short pleasure cruise while we had been in town, and here he was again, slipping in quietly to his moorings off my quay. “They’ll probably stay for the night with us,” I said. “They won’t fly back tonight.”

She glanced up at me. “Couldn’t we go down and meet them?” she inquired. “I mean, it might be nice for them if we did that?”

And so we walked back up the fuzzy to the stable, took the Bentley, and went down to my yard. We got there before the Irene; I took the yard punt and we went out to the moorings on the calm evening water to wait until they came. Near the mooring buoy I pulled in oars, and we sat and drifted, smoking and talking till they came.

The vessel came slowly into sight, more or less becalmed among the hills, drifting slowly into moorings on the flood with the light airs. Stenning is like me, he never motors, if he can avoid it, in a yacht. Joan was at the helm, anxiously striving with the erratic airs; the vessel came slowly to us, with Stenning busy forward with the gear. He dropped the foresail and set up his topping lift, then with the boat hook in his hand he turned and hailed us as they drifted slowly close.

“Been far?” I asked.

“Only to Salcombe and the Yealm,” he said. “This is a holiday, this is.”

He caught his mooring deftly and pulled the chain on board; the vessel turned slowly and swung to the tide. I pulled the punt alongside and we went on board.

I went forward to help Stenning with the main; Mollie went below with Joan. “You’re not going back tonight, are you?” I asked. “I’ve got a lot I want to talk to you about.”

He cocked an eye at me. “About this other business?”

I nodded.

“Right,” he said; “we’ll stay and drink your port for you.” Stenning has a practical mind.

We gathered up their belongings and transferred them to the punt, and squared up the vessel for the night. One of the advantages of a shipyard is that you can bring your yacht in and leave her more or less as she arrives, secure in the knowledge that she will be properly attended to. We got the sail covers on and locked the cabin up, and then we were ready to depart.

Dinner that evening was a pretty cheerful meal. Joan and Stenning were fit and sunburned with their little cruise, and in good spirits. I was surprised and pleased, too, to see how well Mollie was going with them. She had lost her shyness and was chatting to them freely about her life up in the North, with little anecdotes about the people she had met and places she had seen. But she didn’t like the North, she said. The South was ever so much nicer, with the sea and everything.

She talked a lot about the sea. She was always wanting to know things about it—why the tide went up and down the coast instead of coming in and out, and whether seagulls went south for the winter, and how far out to sea they went. Funny questions of that sort that seemed inspired by nothing but sheer interest—and she never forgot anything I told her in that way. I found her very quick.

I sat with Stenning that evening when the ladies had gone out, and over the port I told him all that had happened in the last four days. Rather to my surprise, I found him seriously concerned about Gordon. He has had more experience of the rough–and–tumble side of life than I have had, and he was by no means certain that the police had power to protect informers from the remainder of the gang. He pointed out what would happen to Gordon if this thing had happened in America; he would have been ‘taken for a ride’, and nobody would be able to do much about it. Certainly this was not America, but the ways of gunmen were becoming universal in the world. He thought that we were taking a considerable risk.

He was intensely interested in the whole affair. “I must go back tomorrow,” he said. “I’m tied up with an appointment that I’ve got to keep. But if it’s any help to you, I’ll come down for a day or two after that—when this next landing’s due to be made.” He paused. “I don’t think I’d impress it upon Joan,” he said. “I’d like to see Irene on the slip, and I’d put it that way.”

I told him that that would help a lot. It would be good to have Stenning by my side if there was any trouble coming, and it was good of him to make the offer.

It was still light when we went through into the next room. I had some matters that I wanted to discuss with Joan, and so I cut her out from Stenning and Mollie, and we went walking down the garden in the dusk, talking of little, casual things, until we reached the rose garden and sat a little on the stone balustrade looking away up river to the town. I came to the end of my trivialities down there, and blurted out:

“I came down here because I wanted to talk to you about marrying.”

There was a little silence after I said that; she did not reply at once. In the dim light her cigarette glowed softly as she drew. She blew the smoke out and inquired:

“You’re not married now, are you, Malcolm?”

I shook my head. “Not yet. I hope I’m going to be soon.” I stood and eyed her in the dusk. “You’re the only one of my relations that I give a damn about, and I’d somehow rather that you knew about it first.”

“It’s this girl here, is it?” she asked.

“I shall be asking her if she will marry me, quite soon,” I said.

Joan didn’t say anything to that, and her silence seemed like a rebuke to me. I wanted to explain to her, and so I said: “Even with all the money that I’ve got to give them, the sort of girl I want never falls for me. That’s idealism, I suppose. Seems to me that the present–day girl has a higher set of ideals than ever before—and I should know. I’ve tried no less than six times since the war, and failed, with all my money.” I laughed. “I must say, it’s been an interesting experience. Most instructive.”

Joan leaned forward suddenly, and touched my arm as I laughed. “Poor old Malcolm,” she said quietly.

I said, a little uncertainly: “I’ve got a chance of getting married now. I can’t go on like this, living alone. Dixon was right. I’ve tumbled on somebody who really cares for me at last—and not for my money, either. And I’m going to ask her to marry me.” I glanced at her. “I thought you’d better know.”

Joan said: “I see.”

Something in her tone pierced home and stung me up, and I said harshly: “All right. I know you think I’m messing up my life by marrying a girl like that. You needn’t put it into words.”

In the dim light I saw her looking up at me. “Well, old boy,” she said, “whatever you do now you couldn’t make it any worse, could you? Living alone, like you’ve been doing all these years.”

I stared at her blankly. “You think I’m doing the right thing?” I asked slowly. I had not thought that she would take it quite like that.

She stood up from the balustrade. “Oh, Malcolm,” she burst out, “you are so slow. I don’t believe you know yet what you’ve got. I don’t care where she comes from, or who her people are. You’ve got a girl in ten thousand. She simply adores you. She’s learnt your ways—she knows you better than I do myself. She’s even learning about boats and the sea, because that’s what you like. Do you mean to say that you can’t see it for yourself?”

I said: “I can see it for myself all right. But I didn’t think it was so plain to other people.”

She laughed. “My dear,” she said, “you give the game away a fresh way every five minutes—both of you.”

She threw her cigarette away and came a little closer to me. “Malcolm,” she said, “I think she’ll make you a good wife, and I think that you’ll be happy. Don’t worry about what people will say. The family won’t like it, but that doesn’t matter two hoots. I’ve had my share of that, and I do know.”

“The times are changing,” I said absently. “The family have got to learn.”

She nodded in the dusk. “It’s not such good fun teaching them, though,” she said ruefully. She looked up at me. “You must be gentle with her, Malcolm. Sometimes she won’t do things the way you like them done, sometimes she’ll say the wrong thing and make you look a fool. But she’ll only do it once. You’ll find she never makes the same mistake again. And she’ll be worth a little trouble on your part.”

It was so dark that I could hardly see as she stood beside me. “It’s good of you to talk like that,” I said. “I’d like to feel she had a friend in you.”

She said: “Oh, Malcolm! Give me another cigarette.” And when I had supplied a light for it she said: “You knew that you could count on me. We’ve never spoken of it, but didn’t you do the same for me, when I married Philip? You know, you were the only one of the relations who ever made him feel at home. And I know about the time at Courton, just after we became engaged.”

I laughed. “I didn’t cut much ice for you down there,” I said. “I’m not a hunting man, and that ended it.”

“I know they’re difficult,” she said. “But you went, and months afterwards I heard that you’d been there, and standing up for us. You don’t think I’ve forgotten that, do you?”

“No, Lady Stenning,” I said whimsically, “I don’t.”

She laughed. “Poor Philip! They put his garage rent up half–a–crown when he became a knight—he was furious!” And then more seriously she said: “Class doesn’t matter half so much these days. I wouldn’t change if I could have my time again, and you won’t want to either. Let me know as soon as she’s accepted you, and I’ll come down and see her, and we’ll go and see the family together.”

We moved towards the house. “I’ll hold you to that promise,” I remarked.

Joan and Stenning left next morning, after an early breakfast. Mollie and I went with them to the field and pulled the Moth out from its barn, and stood and watched while Stenning started it up and went all round it with a watchful eye. He ran it up and throttled back; then we packed all their gear into it and Joan got in. Stenning drew me on one side.

“I’m free any time after three o’clock today,” he said. “Unless I let you know I’ll be down here the day after tomorrow, in the afternoon. If you want me before that, give me a ring at the office, and I’ll be with you any time.”

He got into the cockpit and took off. The Moth slipped up into the air over the hedge, turned over the harbour, and dwindled away into a cloudy sky.

The day was overcast and clouding up, with a slowly falling barometer. It looked as if the fine weather was over for the time.

I turned and slipped an arm through Mollie’s, and we went back to the house. After my absence I had business waiting for me at the yard; I left her at the house to look after herself for the morning, and went down to my office to get things squared up.

I found that nothing at the office wanted squaring up so much as did my personal affairs. I sat in my office staring at the calendar and absently polishing the telephone with a duster, and wondered how I was going to propose to Mollie. I had treated this part of the business as a detail up till now, but now that I was up against it it didn’t look so easy after all.

I did very little work that morning beyond opening my letters, and went up to the house with an uneasy mind. We lunched together and I asked her what she had been doing; it seemed that she had spent the morning in the garden and down by the sea. It had grown too cold to bathe with any comfort, and she was no cold water bather at the best of times. I noticed when we went into the library that there was a gap where Mortimer’s Naval History had been. So she had had another look at that. I found later that she had taken it upstairs to pore over.

It was while we were sitting in the library over coffee that the telephone bell rang. I lifted the receiver, and it was Fedden, speaking from his house.

He said: “I’ve just had a call from the Yard. It seems that they’ve had news from Gloucester.”

“Oh,” I said. “What’s that?”

“The man called Palmer called on Gordon this morning, and gave him Friday night, the day after tomorrow, for the landing of the next batch of arms. Unfortunately, the man got away.”

“Friday night?” I said. “That’s earlier than was expected.”

“Only a day or two. But the unfortunate part is that the man Palmer got away. The police weren’t quick enough.”

I asked: “Does he know that information has been laid?”

“I don’t know,” said Fedden. “I imagine that he does.”

“Gordon must have protection, then,” I said. “What’s happening about that?”

“That’s all right—that has been thought of. Gordon is on his way back to the Yard this afternoon. I think that Norman may bring him down with him tomorrow—we shall want him for identification if we get the boat.”

“You’re trying for the boat?” I asked.

“Oh, certainly. I am arranging that side of it here.”

“Do you want any help from me?” I asked. “I’ve got that tug.”

He considered. “Look here,” he said, “could you come down and have a chat?”

“I’ll come down now,” I said.